{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man documented his youthful trek from Indiana to Florida in his A Thousand-Mile Walk To The Gulf. This man opposed a common ally, Gifford Pinchot, over the construction of a dam in the Hetch Hetchy Valley in the aftermath of the San Francisco fire. In 1903, he invited Theodore Roosevelt on a camping trip that inspired the President to transfer Yosemite to the U.S. government. For ten points, name this American conservationist, the founder of the Sierra Club.",
      "answer": "John Muir"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leo Gorcey demanded $400 for his inclusion in this artwork. Jann Haworth and Peter Blake produced this work, which features three depictions of Shirley Temple and one of Stu Sutcliffe. Gandhi and Hitler were removed from this artwork, whose central figures wear yellow, pink, blue, and red military uniforms. Dozens of cardboard cutouts are arranged in the background of, for ten points, what artwork that was mass produced with a record that includes “A Day in the Life” and “Lucy in the Sky with Diamonds” by The Beatles?",
      "answer": "the album cover for Sgt. Pepper’s Lonely Hearts Club Band"
    },
    {
      "question": "The last monarch of this country became the only European monarch to be later elected Prime Minister. Theodor Dannecker’s attempt to have this country’s Jewish population deported were resisted by Tsar Boris III. One dissident from this country was murdered in the Umbrella Incident. This home of Georgi Markov was ruled by communist Todor Zhivkov. Byzantine Emperor Basil II was known as the “slayer” of this country’s people. For ten points, name this European country with capital Sofia.",
      "answer": "Bulgaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "Esther Peterson opposed this legislation in favor of “specific bills for specific ills.” Support for it was removed from the Republican platform in 1980. Its proponents cite Coleman v. Miller as precedent allowing a “three-state strategy” for its adoption. A campaign against this legislation was led by the Eagle Forum’s Phyllis Schlafly, who worried it would discriminate against housewives. Alice Paul first proposed, for ten points, what non-ratified constitutional amendment that would outlaw discrimination based on sex?",
      "answer": "Equal Rights Amendment or ERA"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a teenager, this ruler put down a rebellion led by Jhujhar Singh. The Battle of Tilpat was a victory for this ruler, which resulted in the end of the Jat uprising led by Gokula. This ruler established a system of law known as Fatawa-e-Alamgiri. This ruler reinstated the jizya tax for non-Muslims, which had been abolished by Akbar the Great. This ruler’s mother was laid to rest in the Taj Mahal. For ten points, name this Mughal emperor and son of Shah Jahan.",
      "answer": "Aurangzeb"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s rise to power was secured after the arrest of Osiel Cardenas. Early in his career, he broke an alliance with the Beltran Leyva, and his men accidentally killed the archbishop Juan Ocampos during a battle in Tijuana. This man prompted a federal reaction from Jose Calderon when his hit squad killed the head of the Juarez cartel in a shopping mall. After a second arrest, he escaped through a tunnel in July of 2015. For ten points, name this leader of the Sinaloa cartel who was interviewed by Sean Penn prior to his third arrest in 2016.",
      "answer": [
        "El Chapo",
        "Joaquin Archivaldo Guzm´an Loera"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this ruler’s court were tried for treason in the Merciless Parliament. One of this ruler’s supporters, Robert de Vere, was defeated outside of Oxford by the forces of the Lords Appellant. This ruler was succeeded by the son of John of Gaunt. This son of Edward the Black Prince attempted to collect poll taxes, leading to Wat Tyler’s Peasants’ Revolt. For ten points, name this last Plantagenet King of England who was forced to abdicate by Henry IV, leading to the War of the Roses.",
      "answer": "Richard III of England"
    },
    {
      "question": "Future governor George McDuffie led a boycott in response to this act. It was unusually proposed by Southern Democrats, who planned it to be voted down by New England Whigs opposed to its impact on wool imports. This protectionist act was expected to be repealed with the defeat of John Quincy Adams. The South Carolina Exposition and Protest was written by John Calhoun in opposition to, for ten points, what 1828 tariff, the highest ever in American history, which triggered the Nullification Crisis four years later?",
      "answer": [
        "Tariff of Abominations",
        "Tarif f of 1828 before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1995, seven hostages from this country were able to overpower their Taliban captors and fly home. During another hostage crisis, this country was criticized for indiscriminately flooding a theater with poison gas. On “Knowledge Day” in 2004, terrorists demanding independence from this country occupied a school in Beslan; nearly 200 children died in that siege in North Ossetia. For ten points, name this country, which controls Chechnya.",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work describes how discipline learned in a former home country was not needed in America in the section “The Dilemma of Virtue.” This work was criticized for over-reliance on interviews with Robert Hashima and people kept at Manzanar and other internment camps, as its author could not travel to the subject country during wartime. Shame culture and guilt culture were compared in, for ten points, what 1946 study of Japanese culture by Ruth Benedict?",
      "answer": "The Chrysanthemum and the Sword"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alpamayo is located in this country’s Cordillera Blanca mountain range. The Norte Chico civilization lived in this modern day country, which built the city of Caral. Ramon Castilla led this country during a period of prosperity known as the Guano Era, having won its independence a few decades earlier after the Battle of Ayacucho. The western portion of the Altiplano lies in this country, which shares Lake Titicaca with its southeastern neighbor, Bolivia. For ten points, name this Andean country with capital at Lima.",
        "answer": "Peru"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lake Titicaca is the largest lake in South America; though this body of water is larger in area, it is generally considered a brackish bay. This body of water holds 15% of the oil reserves of the only South American country to be a founding member of OPEC.",
        "answer": "Lake Maracaibo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, in response to Quaker George Logan’s attempt to create peace, Congress banned citizens from making unauthorized international diplomacy. The Retaliation was captured and re-captured in this conflict, which was ended by a treaty signed at Mortefontaine, which dissolved an alliance created in 1778. This event was caused by a breakdown in diplomatic relations regarding American debt owed to the pre-revolutionary government in France. The XYZ Affair was one cause of, for ten points, what officially-not-declared war that lasted from 1798 to 1800.",
        "answer": "Quasi-War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the XYZ Affair, Talleyrand preferred to meet with this American diplomat, a future Vice President, who traveled to France with Charles Pinckney and John Marshall.",
        "answer": "Elbridge Gerry"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Research on these mathematical objects concerns improving on Prim’s and Kruskal’s algorithms for finding minimal spanning trees within these objects. The traveling salesman problem attempts to find an optimal Hamiltonian cycle through these objects. One of these was generated in 1736 by Leonhard Euler by transforming a city map of Konigsberg into an abstract diagram focusing on its seven bridges. For ten points, name these mathematical objects which consist of edges connecting nodes.",
        "answer": [
          "graphs",
          "graph theory"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This theorem regarding planar graphs was conjectured in the 19th century by English cartographers but not proven until the 1970s by Appel and Haken, using a computer to check nearly 2,000 cases.",
        "answer": [
          "four-color map theorem",
          "any description explaining that contiguous planar maps can be colored using only four colors"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One fresco in this city was allegedly painted in the Salone dei Cinquecento by Leonardo da Vinci, and depicted this city’s victory at the Battle of Anghiari. It was betrayed by Bocca degli Abati in a battle against its archrival Siena, leading to its defeat at Montaperti. The Italian invasion of Charles VIII led to the ousting of one prominent family in this city-state, leading to the rule of a man who came into conflict with Alexander VI and sponsored the Bonfire of the Vanities. Girolamo Savonarola ruled briefly in, for ten points, what Tuscan city-state that was ruled by the Medici?",
        "answer": "Florence"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Florence’s main rivals were Siena and this other Tuscan city, which Florence conquered in 1406. Lorenzo Ghiberti’s bronze doors were meant to rival those on this maritime city’s Baptistry.",
        "answer": "Pisa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Newsweek cover about this conflict depicts the Hermes with the caption “The Empire Strikes Back.” Mount Tumbledown was captured in this war, which included landings at San Carlos Water and fighting at Goose Green. Exocet missiles helped sink the Sheffield in this war, in which the General Belgrano was also sunk. The capture of South Georgia Island triggered, for ten points, what war in which Leopoldo Galtieri attempted to reclaim the Malvinas Islands from the United Kingdom?",
        "answer": "Falklands War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly after the battle of Goose Green, this British special operations unit was deployed to capture Mount Kent.",
        "answer": "Special Air Service"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this man’s buildings was derided as a crypto-Communist “threat to the New America” by House Beautiful magazine in 1953. That building inspired a similar house by this man’s student, Philip Johnson. This creator of the glass-clad Farnsworth House succeeded Hannes Meyer as the third director of a design school that was closed in 1933 under pressure from the Nazis. For ten points, what modernist architect and final director of the Bauhaus coined the phrase “less is more?”",
        "answer": "Ludwig Mies van der Rohe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ludwig Mies van der Rohe designed an iconic chair for the German Pavilion of the 1929 World’s Fair in this city, also home to Park Guell.",
        "answer": "Barcelona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side withdrew from this battle in Operation Ke. This battle was roughly simultaneous with naval engagements at Cape Esperance and Santa Cruz. In this battle, codenamed Operation Watchtower, a midnight raid on Tulagi allowed the securing of a landing area for the Cactus Air Force at Henderson Field. Following this battle, MacArthur was able to begin the process of “island hopping”. For ten points, name this 1942 battle in the Solomon Islands, an Allied victory that allowed U.S. forces to start the Pacific offensive.",
        "answer": "Guadalcanal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Japanese admiral, who ordered the attack on Pearl Harbor, was shot down during a Pacific inspection tour a few months after his defeat at Guadalcanal.",
        "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Cardwell military reforms took place under this man. This politician signed the treaty of Kilmainham with Charles Parnell, and he used his own money to save “fallen women.” The Bulgarian horrors were denounced in the Midlothian campaign of this politician who was ousted by Lord Salisbury following the death of “Chinese” Gordon. This supporter of Irish Home Rule was less liked by Queen Victoria than his liberal rival. For ten points, name this conservative Prime Minister and heated rival of Benjamin Disraeli.",
        "answer": "William Gladstone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”Chinese” Gordon’s death in this country, which faced the Mahdist uprising, was a severe blow to Gladstone’s political career.",
        "answer": "Sudan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The New Deal",
      "prompt": "Names or abbreviations acceptable. Which New Deal agency or program...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Built hydroelectric dams in Tennessee?",
          "answer": "Tennessee Valley Authority or TVA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paid its first monthly retirement benefit to Ida May Fuller in January 1941?",
          "answer": "Social Security Administration or SSA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Restored faith in banks by insuring the money held in certain accounts?",
          "answer": "Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or FDIC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Developed natural resources by employing young, unemployed men, who sent most of their wages back home?",
          "answer": "Civilian Conservation Corps or CCC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Employed millions in public works projects under Harry Hopkins?",
          "answer": "Works Progress Administration or WPA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Enforces regulations on financial trading, including 2002’s Sarbanes-Oxley Act?",
          "answer": "Securities and Exchange Commission or SEC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paid farmers to reduce their production, thereby increasing prices?",
          "answer": "Agricultural Adjustment Act or AAA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discriminated against African-Americans by “redlining,” a process that prevented mortgage investment in minority areas?",
          "answer": "Federal Housing Administration or FHA"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nazi Germany",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Four-armed symbol used to represent the Third Reich.",
          "answer": "swastika"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country invaded on September 1, 1939, triggering World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Poland",
            "Second Polish Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Code name for the Nazi invasion of the Soviet Union, named for a leader of the Holy Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primarily-German speaking area of Czechoslovakia that was invaded and annexed in March 1939.",
          "answer": "Sudetenland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy Fuhrer who was captured in Scotland after trying to make peace with the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": "Rudolf Hess"
        },
        {
          "question": "SA leader accused of trying to overthrow Hitler, who was arrested and killed on July 1, 1934.",
          "answer": "Ernst Rohm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessful 1944 plan to assassinate Hitler via a bomb at the Wolf’s Lair, orchestrated by Claus von Stauffenberg.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Valkyrie",
            "July 20th plot"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Hitler student group at the University of Munich, six members of which were executed in 1943 for distributing pamphlets.",
          "answer": "The White Rose"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANZAC Cities",
      "prompt": "Which city in Australia or New Zealand...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Lies on the Cook Strait between the North and South Islands and is home to New Zealand’s parliament?",
          "answer": "Wellington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was designed by the Griffins as a planned capital city, whose land was removed from New South Wales?",
          "answer": "Canberra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was visited by the HMS Beagle in 1839, then named for its most famous passenger?",
          "answer": "Darwin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is eight miles north of Botany Bay, where James Cook landed the Endeavour ?",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hosts the Australian Open tennis tournament and is the largest city in Victoria?",
          "answer": "Melbourne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was struck by a 6.3 magnitude earthquake in 2011, causing its population to fall to third-highest in New Zealand?",
          "answer": "Christchurch"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the base for Australian-Antarctic operations and is the capital of Tasmania?",
          "answer": "Hobart"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lies on the Murray River and was named for King William IV’s wife?",
          "answer": "Adelaide"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader issued the seisachtheia [says-ACK-the-uh], which cancelled debts and ended slave labor as a means of paying debts. He organized the boule as a council of 400 citizens, who were eligible to serve if they produced 200 medimnoi of goods or more; that council was expanded to 500 by (20 pts)",
        "Cleisthenes [KLICE-the-nees]. The power of the Areopagus was reduced by this man’s reforms, which preserved (10 pts)",
        "Draco’s punishments for homicide. For ten points, name this leader who reformed the Athenian constitution in the early 6th century BC."
      ],
      "answer": "Solon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man played Luis Fernandez, a POW along side Michael Caine’s Captain John Colby, in 1981’s Victory , inspired by the “Death Match” played in Start Stadium in Ukraine. This athlete, who never lost a match while playing alongside Garrincha, remains the only player to win three (20 pts)",
        "FIFA World Cups. He was declared a “national treasure,” preventing a transfer to Europe from Santos for 18 years before he joined the NASL’s (10 pts)",
        "New York Cosmos. For ten points, name this legendary Brazilian forward, widely considered the best soccer player of the 20th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Pele or Edson Arantes do Nascimento"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In what is now this city, Colonel William Shy died defending a hill now named for him. Shortly after losing at Franklin, John Bell Hood’s army was decisively beaten again over two days in this city, ending his military career. A (20 pts)",
        "convention held in this city brought southern delegates together to discuss the Compromise of 1850, but did not advocate secession. This city became the last Confederate state (10 pts)",
        "capital to secede and the first to be taken by Union forces, who arrived shortly after winning at Fort Donelson. For ten points, name this city on the Cumberland River, from which Andrew Johnson served as Military Governor of Tennessee."
      ],
      "answer": "Nashville"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer reused a march from his unfinished opera Undine for the Allegretto of his second symphony, which quoted three Ukrainian folk songs. He wrote a piece to benefit wounded soldiers in the Turko-Serbian war. Nikolai Rubenstein rejected his first piano concerto, which (20 pts)",
        "Van Cliburn performed in Moscow in 1958 to win his namesake piano competition. This composer of the Marche Slave and Little Russian Symphony wrote another work featuring (10 pts)",
        "“La Marseillaise,” “God Save The Tsar,” and some cannon fire. For ten points, name this Russian composer of the 1812 Overture."
      ],
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group created settlements known as “reductions” to convert the Tupi-Guarani in Paraguay. The bull Regimini militantis Ecclesiae approved of this group’s formation, but limited it to 60 members until (20 pts)",
        "Pope Julius III removed that limit. One member of this group, Jean de Br´ebeuf integrated settlers of New France with the Hurons, and members of this group who traveled to (10 pts)",
        "Asia included Matteo Ricci and St. Francis Xavier. The motto “Ad maiorem Dei gloriam” is held by, for ten points, what Catholic counter-reformation group founded by Ignatius of Loyola?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Society of Jesus",
        "Jesuits"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party reduced working time to 35 hours per week with the Aubry laws. One winning candidate from this party won on the 110 Propositions, which involved the creation of a solidarity tax on wealth. The first cohabitation took place between that party leader and (20 pts)",
        "Jacques Chirac from 1986-1988. Dominique Strauss-Kahn, the former head of the IMF, was a member of this party, whose current head has stepped up (10 pts)",
        "attacks in the Middle East in response to the Bataclan shootings. For ten points, name this French center-left party, whose leaders have included Francois Mitterand and Francois Hollande."
      ],
      "answer": "Socialist Party of France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s regime is the subject of Mario Vargas Llosa’s [yoh-sa’s] The Feast of the Goat . Johnny Abbes Garcia led the SIM, a secret police force under this leader. The OAS imposed sanctions on this leader’s country after he ordered a failed assassination attempt on (20 pts)",
        "Venezuelan president Romulo Betancourt. This leader’s government was responsible for the deaths of thousands of Haitians in the (10 pts)",
        "Parsley massacre, and he was assassinated in an ambush outside Santo Domingo in 1961. For ten points, name this dictator of the Dominican Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the Treaty of Easton reversed some of the provisions of the Walking Purchase. In this war, James Abercrombie blundered by ordering a frontal assault with no artillery support at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Carillon. During this war, an army landed at L’Anse-au-Foulon then climbed a high cliff under nightfall; in the ensuing battle, opposing generals Louis-Joseph de (10 pts)",
        "Montcalm and James Wolfe died on the Plains of Abraham, leading to the British conquest of Quebec City. For ten points, name this theater of the Seven Years’ War that cemented British North American colonialism."
      ],
      "answer": "French and Indian War"
    }
  ]
}